Guide to the Manny Harriman Video Oral History Collection ALBA.VIDEO.048
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Manny Harriman Video Oral History Collection
Bulk, 1985-1987
1945-1990
ALBA.VIDEO.048
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
7.5 linear feet (22 boxes)
Manny Harriman (1919-1997) was a veteran of both the Spanish Civil War (he served under his birth name, Samuel Nahman) and World War II who later pursued careers in tool and die making and publishing. Following his first return trip to Spain in 1977, Harriman became interested in the history of his fellow Spanish Civil War veterans. The collection consists of oral history interviews he began videotaping in 1985 with veterans and/or their surviving relatives and friends across the country. The collection also contains a small number of recordings of VALB political activities during the mid-1980s, particularly around aid to Nicaragua. Harriman captured the personal histories of at least 180 veterans. The interviews cover veterans’ family histories, their motivations for joining the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, their experiences fighting in Spain and later in World War II, and their activities in subsequent years.
Harriman, Manny.
Provenance
This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
A Harriman interview with John Perrrone was donated by Ronald Perrone on January, 2010.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions; however, users cannot screen original videos or audiocassettes. If no viewing copy exists for a requested video or audiocassette, users should consult with archivist regarding cost of duplication.
Historical/Biographical Note
Manny Harriman was born Samuel Nahman on January 19, 1919 in Manhattan to Haim (Herman) Nahman, a shoemaker, and Jennie Nahman. He was the middle one of five children. His parents had both been born in Turkey and were of Sephardic Jewish heritage. Harriman attended school until his early teens, when in the midst of the Great Depression, he began to work with his father in order to help support the family. During the thirties, Harriman was employed as both a shoemaker and a construction worker, and worked on various WPA projects. During this period, he became politically active in New York City, joining the Young Communist League in 1935 and continuing to participate until his departure for Spain. He was also involved with the Workers Alliance and Federation Settlement and participated in strikes of WPA and shoe store workers.
A member of a strongly anti-fascist and politically active family, Harriman volunteered to fight in the Spanish Civil War at age nineteen and left for Spain on May 14, 1938. He was among the last U.S. volunteers to arrive in Spain. He served as a machine gunner. On August 1, 1938, during the attack on Gandesa, he was wounded, and spent almost a month recovering. He returned to the front in September 1938 and fought in the Ebro offensive. During his last days in Spain, he served in Battalion Transmissions.
Harriman returned to the United States on the SS Paris on December 15, 1938. He worked as a machinist and had two children with his wife, Celia Harriman. Drafted in 1942, he served in the U.S. Army Air Corps during World War II. His craft was shot down over Italy, and he spent over a year as a POW in a prison camp in northern Germany. Liberated by the Russians on May 1, 1945, he was later awarded a Purple Heart and the Air Medal. Following World War II, he began an apprenticeship as a tool and die maker under sponsorship from the G.I. Bill, and worked in this trade until 1959. In 1956, during the McCarthy period, he changed his name from Samuel Nahman to Manny Harriman in an attempt to avoid harassment. In addition to forming his own manufacturing business in 1960, Harriman ran a small publishing firm, called The Camelot Publishing Company, along with fellow Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Arthur H. Landis. Harriman helped with research for Landis’ book Spain! The Unfinished Revolution, published by Camelot in 1972. In 1972, Harriman briefly retired and then returned to tool and die making for several years. He eventually settled in Los Angeles.
In 1977, he participated in a trip with seven other veterans to Spain, where they toured Spanish Civil War battlefields. As a result of this trip, Harriman became more involved in Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades (VALB) and interested in documenting the veterans’ histories. He served as editor of The Volunteer, the VALB newsletter, from 1978 until 1983. Following another trip to Spain in 1983, Harriman set out to record the oral histories of all of the remaining veterans, whom he estimated to number 350. He was concerned that only a handful of veterans’ personal histories were well documented.
The videotaping project began in earnest in 1985. Landis and Harriman pitched the idea to Donald (Don) MacLeod, San Francisco Post Historian, Edward (Ed) Bender, San Francisco Post Secretary, and Faiga Duncan, widow of veteran Lowell Duncan. They extended their support, were active in the production process, and provided housing in San Francisco during taping sessions. Along with Landis, Harriman created a questionnaire for use during interviews (see project files in ALBA # 48) that traced the veterans’ personal histories from their parents’ ancestry to their return from World War II and sought to discover the effects of their participation in the Spanish Civil War on the rest of their lives. According to project files, each interviewee was to receive the questionnaire before being interviewed. Harriman’s brother, Ben Nahman, his second wife, Debby Harriman, and LaVerne Grell, son of veteran Fritz Grell, were also active in the production process.
Along with these project volunteers, Harriman began by interviewing 76 veterans in the San Francisco area. Other veterans were interviewed in Los Angeles, San Diego, Washington, New York, Oklahoma, and along the East Coast. The majority of West Coast interviews were completed by early 1986, and New York area interviews were conducted from the summer of 1986 to early 1987. While Harriman conducted the majority of interviews himself, it appears from project correspondence that Duncan and MacLeod may also have served as interviewers. Harriman completed a large portion of the West Coast and New York interviews he had planned, but it appears that he did not complete the entire project as envisioned. He had hoped, for example, to travel to Spain to interview veterans living there, but never made the trip. The project may have been cut short due to lack of funds. Harriman financed much of the project himself and with his family, and received some support from other veterans. He did not, it appears, receive financial assistance from the national office of VALB, though he had at first anticipated receiving such funding. The National Resident Board of VALB and the National Historical Commission both endorsed the project. These endorsements were particularly important in securing veterans’ willingness to be interviewed, as several of them were involved at that time in aid to Nicaragua and were fearful of FBI harassment. By early 1987, Harriman and his team had completed approximately 185 separate interviews, covering the personal histories of more than 180 veterans.
Manny Harriman died on January 22, 1997.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Manny Harriman Oral History Project, contains 209 videocassettes (most camera originals) consisting of approximately 175 separate interviews covering the personal histories of at least 180 Abraham Lincoln Brigade veterans, American Medical Bureau personnel, and Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade organizers. Several of the original 218 videocassettes were not given to ALBA by Harriman or are since missing. Among those veterans who were originally interviewed but whose tapes are since missing are Bernard (Barney) Baley and Joao Marques Albino. The majority of interviews feature surviving veterans, but in cases where the veteran had passed away, interviews were conducted with their widows, surviving children, and friends. Interviews with friends or relatives speaking about a veteran are titled “[Name of veteran] discussed by [name of interviewee]”; interviews with the veterans themselves are titled “[Name of veteran] Interview.”
A duplicate set of these interviews is held by Brandeis University Special Collections.
The interviews cover the following topics: family history and childhood, political activities in the United States, motivations for joining the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, experiences fighting in Spain, repatriation, experiences of discrimination following repatriation, involvement in World War II, and life after the war. Significant interviews (covering three or more videocassettes) include those with Carl Geiser, Irving Goff, Arthur Landis, Vaughn Love, and Steve Nelson.
The series represents a diverse portrait of the veterans still alive during the 1980s, covering more than half of the then-surviving veterans, representing a geographic balance of veterans living in different parts of the country, and including some veterans who were less active in official VALB activities.
Series II: General Subjects, Events, Memorials, etc., is divided into two subseries based on format.
Subseries IIA: Video, consists mostly of recordings of political activities of the Bay Area Post members of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, particularly around humanitarian aid to Nicaragua in protest of U.S. support for the Contras. There are also recordings of memorial services for veterans who passed away during the course of the project.
Subseries IIB: Audio, consists mostly of audiocassettes recorded by Manny Harriman. Most notable are the many cassettes recorded on VALB's trip to Spain in 1983.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series:
Series I: Manny Harriman Oral History Project
Series II: General Subjects, Events, Memorials, etc.
Each item has been assigned a unique number (i.e. ALBA V 48-001), and the collection is arranged in item number order.
In first series, the item number order roughly follows the alphabetical order of the last name of the primary interviewee on each tape; however, due to variations of some veterans' names, a few tapes may fall outside of this alphabetical order. In addition, each tape may contain multiple separate interviews with different veterans.
In the second series, the item number order is entirely alphabetical.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
The Manny Harriman Papers (ALBA 048) contain project files related to these oral histories, including completed personal history questionnaires for many of the veterans interviewed.
Aalto, William.; Bailey, Bill; Bessie, Alvah Cecil, 1904-1985. -- Death and burial; Brown, Archie, 1911-1990.; Burns, Paul, d.1996.; Colodny, Robert Garland.; Dallet, Joe, 1907-1937; Duncan, Faiga; Fasanella, Ralph; Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade.; Geiser, Carl; Goff, Irving.; Grell, LaVerne.; Harriman, Manny.; Landis, Arthur H., 1917-1986; Love, Vaughn; MacLeod, Donald.; Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy.; Merriman, Marion, 1909-; Merriman, Robert Hale; Nelson, Steve, 1903-; Postek, Stanley, 1912-1991; Prago, Albert; Rappaport, Irving.; Roberts, Hilda Bell; Shafran, Jack.; Simon, Mildred Rackley, 1906-2003; Smorodin, Abe.; Steck, Robert.; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Bay Area Post.; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Historical Commission.; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade.; Watt, George, 1913-1994; Audiocassettes.; Los Angeles (Calif.); New York (N.Y.); San Diego (Calif.); San Francisco (Calif.); Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Personal narratives.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Participation, American.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Women.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939.; Videocassettes.
- Series I: Manny Harriman Oral History Project
  - Aalto, William (Bill) discussed by Irving (Irv) Goff, undated (Box 1, Item ALBA V 48-001)
    General note
    Interview with Irving (Irv) Goff about Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran William (Bill) Aalto. Tape also contains Goff discussing other veterans. Also discusses Alex Kunstlich?
  - Acker, Leon discussed by Sylvia Acker, Jul 23, 1985 (Box 1, Item ALBA V 48-002)
    First of two tapes containing interview with Sylvia Acker, widow of Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Leon Acker, who died in Spain in July 1938.
  - Acker, Leon discussed by Sylvia Acker, Jul 23, 1985 (Box 1, Item ALBA V 48-003)
    Second of two tapes containing interview with Sylvia Acker, widow of Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Leon Acker who died in Spain in July 1938.
  - Alexander, Cecil, Freddy [Stozer?], Max Hendler, and [?] Sachs discussed by David (Dave) Thompson, Jul 7, 1985 (Box 1, Item ALBA V 48-004)
    Interview with Dave Thompson about Abraham Lincoln Brigade veterans Cecil Alexander (guerilla commander who died in Spain), Freddy [Stozer?] (deceased), Max Hendler (deceased), and Sachs (first name unknown, deceased).
  - Alexander, Frank Interview, Sep 3, 1985 (Box 1, Item ALBA V 48-005)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Frank Alexander.
  - Alper, Marcus Interview, Sep 1, 1986 (Box 1, Item ALBA V 48-006)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Marcus Alper.
  - Amery, Leopold Alfred Interview, Sep 2, 1986 (Box 1, Item ALBA V 48-007)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Alfred Amery.
  - Anderson, Melvin Interview; Robert (Bob) DuPont discussed by Evelyn DuPont, undated (Box 1, Item ALBA V 48-008)
    Tape contains two interviews. Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Melvin Anderson and interview with Evelyn Du Pont about Robert (Bob) DuPont.
  - Azar, Joseph (Joe) Interview, Jan 24, 1987 (Box 1, Item ALBA V 48-009)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Joe Azar.
  - Bailey, Bill Interview; Lowell Duncan discussed by Faiga Duncan, Feb 27, 1985 (Box 1, Item ALBA V 48-010)
    Tape contains two interviews. Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Bill Bailey and interview with Faiga Duncan, widow of veteran Lowell Duncan.
  - Barr, Reuben Interview; Howard Goddard Interview, Jun 10, 1985 (Box 1, Item ALBA V 48-011)
    Tape contains two interviews. Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Reuben Barr and interview with veteran Howard Goddard.
  - Bell, Everett Raymond Interview, Sep 5, 1986 (Box 1, Item ALBA V 48-012)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Raymond Bell.
  - Berg, Delmer (Danny) Interview, Jul 14, 1985 (Box 2, Item ALBA V 48-013)
    First of two tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Delmer (Danny) Berg.
  - Berg, Delmer (Danny) Interview, Jul 14, 1985 (Box 2, Item ALBA V 48-014)
    Second of two tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Delmer (Danny) Berg.
  - Berkowitz, Norman Interview, Aug 26, 1986 (Box 2, Item ALBA V 48-015)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Norman Berkowitz.
  - Berman, Leopold (Leo) discussed by Mollie Berman, undated (Box 2, Item ALBA V 48-016)
    Interview with Mollie Berman, widow of Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Leo Berman.
  - Bessie, Alvah Memorial; Ambulances from Nicaragua Demonstration, Aug 14, 1985 (Box 2, Item ALBA V 48-017)
    Tape contains recordings with two events. Recording of Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Alvah Bessie's memorial (8/14/1985), and recording of demonstration of ambulances sent to Nicaragua by veterans (7/4/1985).
  - Billings, Marcus (Mark) Interview, Jul 24, 1985 (Box 2, Item ALBA V 48-018)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Mark Billings.
  - Blanc, Esther Interview, Jul 1, 1985 (Box 2, Item ALBA V 48-019)
    Interview with American Medical Bureau nurse Esther Blanc.
  - Bonetti, Frank Interview, undated (Box 2, Item ALBA V 48-020)
    First of two tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Frank Bonetti
  - Bonetti, Frank Interview, undated (Box 2, Item ALBA V 48-021)
    Second of two tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Frank Bonetti
  - Brandt, Joe Interview, Nov 23, 1986 (Box 2, Item ALBA V 48-022)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Joe Brandt.
  - Brown, Archie Interview; Sari Stadt Interview, undated (Box 2, Item ALBA V 48-023)
    Tape contains two interviews. Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Archie Brown, and interview with American Medical Bureau nurse Sari Stadt. Stadt may also discuss her husband, American Medical Bureau dentist Zachary Stadt.
  - Brown, Warner Interview, Aug 20, 1985 (Box 2, Item ALBA V 48-024)
    Interview of Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran[?] Warner Brown.
  - Burns, Paul Interview, Jul 13, 1986 (Box 3, Item ALBA V 48-025)
    First of two tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Paul Burns.
  - Burns, Paul Interview, Aug 19, 1986 (Box 3, Item ALBA V 48-026)
    Second of two tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Paul Burns.
  - Cane, Lawrence (Larry) discussed by Grace Cane-Mason, Jan 17, 1987 (Box 3, Item ALBA V 48-027)
    First of two tapes containing interview with Grace Cane-Mason, widow of Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Larry Cane.
  - Cane, Lawrence (Larry) discussed by Grace Cane-Mason, Jan 17, 1987 (Box 3, Item ALBA V 48-028)
    Second of two tapes containing interview with Grace Cane-Mason, widow of Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Larry Cane.
  - Cannon, Karl Interview, Apr 3, 1985 (Box 3, Item ALBA V 48-029)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Karl Cannon.
  - Chesler, Frank Interview, Apr 18, 1986 (Box 3, Item ALBA V 48-030)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Frank Chesler.
  - Cogswell, Theodore Interview, Sep 7, 1986 (Box 3, Item ALBA V 48-031)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Theodore Cogswell.
  - Colodny, Robert Interview, Jul 24, 1986 (Box 3, Item ALBA V 48-032)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Robert Colodny.
  - Colow, Maury Interview, Sep 25, 1986 (Box 3, Item ALBA V 48-033)
    First of three tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Maury Colow.
  - Colow, Murray Interview, Sep 25, 1986 (Box 3, Item ALBA V 48-034)
    Second of three tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Murray Colow.
  - Colow, Murray Interview, Sep 25, 1986 (Box 3, Item ALBA V 48-035)
    Third of three tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Murray Colow.
  - Corbin, Rudolph (Rudy) Interview; Henry Rubin Interview, undated (Box 3, Item ALBA V 48-036)
    Tape contains two interviews. Second with two tapes containing interview of veteran Rudy Corbin; and interview of Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Henry Rubin.
  - Dallet Jr., Joseph discussed by Peg McIntire, Feb 25, 1987 (Box 4, Item ALBA V 48-037)
    First of two tapes containing interview with Peg McIntire, sister of Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Joseph Dallet, Jr.
  - Dallet Jr., Joseph discussed by Peg McIntire, Feb 25, 1987 (Box 4, Item ALBA V 48-038)
    Second of two tapes containing interview with Peg McIntire, sister of Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Joseph Dallet, Jr.
  - Explanation of Harriman Video Project: Demonstration Tape, undated (Box 4, Item ALBA V 48-039)
    Demonstration tape containing explanation of Manny Harriman's Video Project with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veterans. May contain excerpts of original interview footage.
  - Deutsch, Julius Interview, Jun 25, 1985 (Box 4, Item ALBA V 48-040)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Julius Deutsch
  - DuValle, Pierre Interview, Jul 30, 1985 (Box 4, Item ALBA V 48-041)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Pierre DuValle.
  - Eider, Louis discussed by Kate [Eider?], Jun 25, 1986 (Box 4, Item ALBA V 48-042)
    Interview with Kate [Eider?], wife of Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Louis Eider.
  - Fasanella, Ralph Interview, Sep 23, 1986 (Box 4, Item ALBA V 48-043)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Ralph Fasanella.
  - Frankel, Irving Interview, Mar 10, 1986 (Box 4, Item ALBA V 48-044)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Irving Frankel.
  - Freed, Harry Interview, Apr 4, 1986 (Box 4, Item ALBA V 48-045)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Harry Freed. Also discusses Morris Presser and Bart Van der Schelling.
  - Gayle, Louis (Lou) Interview, Mar 18, 1986 (Box 4, Item ALBA V 48-046)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Lou Gayle.
  - Geiser, Carl Interview, Apr 14, 1985 (Box 4, Item ALBA V 48-047)
    First of seven tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Carl Geiser discussing the history of Spanish Civil War POWs and his book project.
  - Geiser, Carl Interview, undated (Box 4, Item ALBA V 48-048)
    Second of seven tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Carl Geiser discussing the history of Spanish Civil War POWs and his book project.
  - Geiser, Carl Interview, Apr 14, 1985 (Box 5, Item ALBA V 48-049)
    Third of seven tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Carl Geiser discussing the history of Spanish Civil War POWs and his book project.
  - Geiser, Carl Interview, Apr 14, 1985 (Box 5, Item ALBA V 48-050)
    Fourth of seven tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Carl Geiser discussing the history of Spanish Civil War POWs and his book project.
  - Geiser, Carl Interview, Apr 14, 1985 (Box 5, Item ALBA V 48-051)
    Fifth of seven tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Carl Geiser discussing the history of Spanish Civil War POWs and his book project.
  - Geiser, Carl Interview, Apr 14, 1985 (Box 5, Item ALBA V 48-052)
    Sixth of seven tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Carl Geiser discussing the history of Spanish Civil War POWs and his book project.
  - Geiser, Carl Interview, Apr 14, 1985 (Box 5, Item ALBA V 48-053)
    Seventh of seven tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Carl Geiser discussing the history of Spanish Civil War POWs and his book project.
  - Giler, Henry Interview, Apr 5, 1985 (Box 5, Item ALBA V 48-054)
    Interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Henry Giler.
  - Goff, Irving (Irv) Interview, Apr 3, 1985 (Box 5, Item ALBA V 48-055)
    First of five tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Irv Goff. Goff may be discussing fellow veterans Irving Fajans, Alex Kunstlich, Vincent Lossowski, Mike Jiminez, and Hymie[?] Jiminez.
  - Goff, Irving (Irv) Interview, Apr 3, 1985 (Box 5, Item ALBA V 48-056)
    Second of five tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Irv Goff. Goff may be discussing fellow veterans Irving Fajans, Alex Kunstlich, Vincent Lossowski, Mike Jiminez, and Hymie[?] Jiminez.
  - Goff, Irving (Irv) Interview, Apr 3, 1985 (Box 5, Item ALBA V 48-057)
    Third of five tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Irv Goff. Goff may be discussing fellow veterans Irving Fajans, Alex Kunstlich, Vincent Lossowski, Mike Jiminez, and Hymie[?] Jiminez.
  - Goff, Irving (Irv) Interview, undated (Box 5, Item ALBA V 48-058)
    Fourth of five tapes containing interview with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran Irv Goff. Goff may be discussing fellow veterans Irving Fajans, Alex Kunstlich, Vincent Lossowski, Mike Jiminez, and Hymie[?] Jiminez.
  - Goff, Irving (Irv) Interview; VALB Dinner Fundraiser for Nicaragua Ambulances, Apr 14, 1985 (Box 5, Item ALBA V 48-059)